- Where is she?
- Over here.
You saw the suspect?
Details, please. Where? When?
Uh, I was coming out
of the elevator after lunch.
Where was the suspect headed?
Uh, up the stairs, which I thought
was strange
'cause that leads to the roof, right?
It's not just the roof.
It's where Jane works.
- Has anybody seen him?
- Not since this morning.
Cover the exits! All of them!
Use whoever you have to out here!
Hasten slowly.
The target will be armed.
It's locked.
Jane?
- You in there?
- "Yeah, I'm coming out."
"You're gonna have to stand back.
And if you're bearing firearms"
"please lower them."
"Please."
Stand back...
or he dies.
Security guard making rounds this morning
found the body. Multiple stab wounds.
Anything missing from the display case?
Yeah, a Mayan figurine. Gold.
Valued at 200 grand.
- We get an I.D. on the victim?
- Manuel Montero.
He was a professor at the university
in ancient art.
Security cameras show him
entering the museum alone
at 10:25 p.m.
- then he turned off the cameras.
- "Hey, Lisbon."
Look at this.
Meet Caroline...
one of the most well-preserved
tyrannosaurus rex ever discovered.
- Isn't she awesome?
- We've got a dead man over there.
- Dead men I've seen. But this...
- Could we get back to work, please?
Must I justify my every action?
Please observe the rib cage
of our smaller fossilized friend here.
- Is there a rib broken off?
- Exactly.
You think somebody climbed up
there and stole it?
Well, two options...
the first involves cloning.
The second and more likely...
it was used to break a very thick
piece of glass.
Could we get somebody to dust
the stegosaurus for prints, please?
It's not a stegosaurus. It's a triceratops.
- Triceratop... s. Ps.
- S. Ps.
My name is Christo Papadakis.
I am professor of anthropology.
- Did you know the victim?
- Manuel Montero.
He was part-time faculty.
Too busy to teach full-time.
Montero was on the run.
On the run from who?
Nobody. He... he traveled.
He was always running to South America.
- His career was in ruins.
- Well, tough times for everybody.
Not for Montero.
He had a lot of money.
Well, you just said he was in ruins.
Yes, Toltec. Mayan.
Oh. Montero was an archaeologist?
Specializing in Pre-Columbian Art.
Many of the pieces around you are,
uh, on loan from him.
Can you think of anyone
with a reason to kill Montero?
- Well, he was a traitor and...
- Oh, he was a traitor?
Who did he betray?
- Betray? Nobody.
- Well, you just said he was a...
Montero was an honest antiquities dealer.
One of the last.
Most traders these days are looters
and no-good son-of-a-bitches.
So, Montero was a trader...
He traded antiquities, excavated
from South American ruins.
Are you really professional
police officer?
So the missing pendant
belonged to the victim.
Montero liked to visit
the museum after hours
to show his pieces to private buyers.
He had a key to the building
and the security code.
At the heart of any salesman
is showmanship.
And you'd be hard-pressed to find
a more dramatic proscenium than this.
Yeah, smart strategy unless
the buyer doesn't wanna pay.
Stabbed in the back, literally.
Montero probably didn't even
see it coming.
But he had time to think
about it before he died.
Look at his watch.
Wow. That's an ugly watch.
- It's a calculator watch.
- Indeed.
Very useful accessory
for the sales pro on the go.
Is there something typed in there?
It's uh, numbers.
"6-0-7-8."
Supposed to mean something?
Try looking at the numbers upside-down.
It says "Blog".
His cell phone was crushed by the killer
so Montero here improvised.
Call Van Pelt
and see if Montero published a blog.
- I'm ready to go. I've seen enough.
- I haven't.
You know they have mastodons here?
Giant sloths.
And dire wolves. I-I'll catch up.
"But, Mommy, I wanna go."
You can squawk all you like, Mimi.
There's no sleepovers on a school night.
- "I have to."
- No.
"Mommy, that's unfair."
I'm sorry, baby. I gotta go.
- "All right. Love you. Bye."
- Love you, too. Bye.
Forgive the intrusion.
What's this about, Agent LaRoche?
The Todd Johnson case.
I would like to show you a photo
of one of the law enforcement officers
that he murdered.
Did you know this man?
Rance Howard.
C.H.P. officer.
Very popular.
A lot of our agents were close to him.
Some more than others.
There's a rumor that you and Howard
were intimately involved.
Is that true?
- Excuse me?
- Simple question.
Simple answer...
what the hell is that to you
or anybody else?
Johnson was set on fire...
a crime of passion
if there ever was one.
If you were having an affair
with one of Johnson's victims
you had passion and motive.
Your investigation seems to hinge
on what you may have read
on a bathroom wall.
Good luck with that, Agent LaRoche.
- Background on Montero.
- What do we know about him?
Single, self-employed, spent half his time
abroad importing ancient art.
- Sold it from a warehouse in San Francisco.
- Family?
Parents retired in Florida.
They'll be on the next flight here.
Hey, boss. I looked into the blog.
Montero did publish one...
"I dig dead people."
Archaeology humor. Cute.
Anything useful?
A lot of self-promotional entries
about his relic-hunting adventures.
But three weeks ago
he came back from a trip to Columbia
with the gold pendant that was stolen
from the museum.
After Montero blogged about it
a private buyer posted an anonymous
e-mail to arrange a viewing.
Did you put a trace on the e-mail?
Not me. FBI's computer forensics lab.
One of the perks of having a fiancé
with the Feds.
Preliminary forensic report.
You're gonna have dozens of prints
from the triceratops skeleton.
It's gonna take a while
to process them, though.
While we're waiting on forensics,
let's work on developing some leads.
Hey, you said that Montero
had a warehouse?
Yeah, in the Mission District.
But there's something else.
I ran his financials.
The profits from his company
have been going up at a time
when other art and antiquity
dealers are closing shop.
- Closing shop? Why?
- Repatriation laws.
Countries are now suing for the return
of their cultural treasures.
You and Rigsby go to the warehouse.
See if you can find anything.
Alright.
- Hi, Jane.
- Hey.
The boys are working
on the parking lot today.
- Need you to park underground.
- Oh, no problem.
That kid of yours, Jim... Is he
into dinosaurs and prehistoric stuff?
Sure loves his mother.
Here. Give him this.
It's a replica of a dire wolf's tooth.
Thanks. Look at that.
Have a good day.
- What?
- I didn't say anything.
You were thinking it.
- Mentalizing me.
- You can tell?
I can read it on your face.
So stop.
Well, if you can read it on my face,
then you're mentalizing me.
So you stop.
Oh. No, on second thought, keep going.
- What am I thinking?
- Please go away, Jane.
Nope. That's wrong. Try again.
You're thinking I'm freaking out
because some fool spread a rumor
that I was having an affair
with Rance Howard.
The C.H.P. officer?
You're the one thinking it.
I feel naked.
There's only one person that has this
singular effect on people.
You've been LaRoched, haven't you?
- I suppose I have.
- Well, there's no shame in it.
We're all pots in his kitchen.
And he's a sous-chef
just waiting for one of us to boil over.
I won't give him the satisfaction.
- Of course not. Did you?
- Did I what?
Did you have an affair
with Rance Howard?
My personal life is my personal life.
Nobody else has the right to it.
Well you're wrong about that.
LaRoche does.
Whatever the truth is
I wouldn't try to hide it from him.
He'll find out eventually.
It's our lucky day, buddy.
See that taco truck
just as we got off the freeway?
- That taco truck's always there.
- Oh, yeah.
A little carne asada after we check
out the warehouse?
- "Super good."
- No.
Why not?
I don't wanna cross hobo alley
to order lunch from a truck
that's near the sewage ditch
under the freeway.
But there's tacos there.
This is the warehouse.
Let's check out the back.
Hey!
CBI. Who's in charge here?
"Estamos con la policía.
Quién está a cargo?"
Maybe they don't speak Spanish.
Maybe you don't.
You guys work for Montero?
Gun!
Cover me!
"Idiot."
Throw out your weapon!
"La Pistola!"
Do it now!
Step into clear view!
Hands in the air!
Face down on the ground.
Hands out to your sides. Do it now.
Hey! Hey, hey, easy! Easy!
Yeah, now he understands English.
So...
What kinda ancient art you boys
selling today, huh?
Roberto Salvador.
You're on a work visa from Columbia.
So you work for Montero?
Could be.
Could be Montero work for me.
Attitude. Really?
Uh, where are you going?
To write you up on charges
of running guns
resisting arrest, attempted murder...
"Hey, hey, calm down."
I only shot at you
because you shot at me.
What... what can I do here?
I got a family, you know.
I wanna see them again.
You answer my questions.
No attitude.
Maybe we'll forget
about the attempted murder.
Good. Sit down.
Put your feet up.
Why did Montero hire you?
- To run his shipping operation.
- Weapons or antiquities?
Both.
Manuel was an honest businessman
for many years
but the profit in those museum
pieces went away.
Too many legal barriers.
Politicians, criminals to bribe.
So Montero started trafficking guns.
He had his company all set up.
He could ship them to South America,
no questions asked
then trade them for all the black
market antiquities he could handle.
Did Montero have any enemies?
No. He was beloved.
In Colombia, they called him
"El Profesor."
What do you think?
Well, it has a certain pulp appeal
as far as mysteries go...
murder in the museum,
stolen Mayan gold
Colombian gun runners...
But it's a tawdry work of fiction
completely made up.
Oh, I'm pretty sure Montero's dead.
Yes, but not for the reasons
that we're being led to believe.
How can you tell?
I find it easier to show than to tell.
Uh, excuse me.
Could you please tell me
who Montero was trading weapons to
in South America?
Answer the question.
- Cartels, gangs, private armies.
- Oh, makes sense.
If they wanted him dead,
how would they go about that?
You would never know how.
He would just...
disappear.
Okay.
And if the body just happened
to be found miraculously
where might that be?
Uh, a mass grave. Side of a road.
We found him stabbed
and bled out in a public museum.
Would you kill a man that way?
Hell, no. Heh. Too high-risk.
Somebody killed Montero for reasons
that had nothing to do
with Pre-Columbian art
and nothing to do
with Colombian cartels.
That's just what the killer
wanted us to think.
Oh, I asked Conway
over at Gambling Control
to join our investigation
into the loan-shark syndicate.
Conway's a good man,
but he can talk the paint off a car.
Don't let him run the briefings.
- Director Bertram.
- J.J., you waiting for me?
Special Agent Hightower, actually.
- Good night.
- Night.
A visual reconstruction
of the night of Todd Johnson's murder
based on security footage
activity logs
and 86 hours of interviews.
Nice project board.
Bet you won a few science fairs.
I won all of them.
This is the holding cell
where Johnson was burned alive.
The circles indicate
the location of people within CBI
moments before his murder.
My research revealed
that this group of people did not
have the security clearance
to enter the holding area.
This group...
they were all too far away
to have set the fire.
These...
all have at least two or more witnesses
who can verify
their location at the time of the attack.
Five circles.
- This one is you.
- Is it?
I offer you this...
Five suspects...
within striking distance of Johnson
each one highly capable
but only one...
with a clear motive.
Okay.
I was sleeping with Officer Howard.
But I didn't...
I-I...
At the time Howard was killed,
we were no longer together.
- His choice or yours?
- Mutual decision.
It... It... It wasn't...
- Did you set Todd Johnson on fire?
- No, I did not.
You must have been...
grieving
about Howard.
How did you deal with that?
I got on my knees and I asked the Lord
for strength and forgiveness.
That's how I dealt with that.
You might wanna write that down.
I think I'll remember it.
"Hey, Jane. You were right."
Well, of course. What instance
of rightness are we speaking of?
Yesterday, when you said
Montero was killed for reasons
having nothing to do
with the stolen artifacts.
So I stayed up late last night
and I researched his personal life.
Someone should stay up
and research yours.
You're never gonna guess
where he grew up.
Then I won't even try.
- Vineland, California.
- How did you do that?
- I followed your lips. Vineland?
Hometown of infamous cop killer
Todd Johnson?
Follow me.
Did you print that photo
I sent you last night?
Yep. That's Johnson and Montero.
They were co-captains of their
high school football team.
Are you getting this?
Our murder victim was best friends
with the serial cop killer.
It's a great photo.
After I put that together I asked Cho
to go to Montero's warehouse last night
see if he could find any other links.
Tell him what you found.
The guns Montero was running?
He bought them from gun shops.
Paid people with clean records
to make the buys.
Montero has a record of every
purchase, including serial numbers.
Let me guess. You traced
one of the serial numbers
back to a weapon that Montero
gave to his buddy Johnson.
That's right. Same weapon
Johnson used to kill his victims.
Have you mentioned
any of this to LaRoche?
I set a briefing
with top brass in ten minutes.
LaRoche, Bertram, and Hightower
will all be there.
- Ten minutes, Cho.
- Yep.
Uh, excuse me.
I'm looking for the fingerprint lab.
That's... that's me. Who are... you?
Patrick Jane.
Any luck with the curious case
of the triceratops rib?
Look, I don't really...
function efficiently under pressure,
so...
Hey, no pressure. Just wondering
if you'd found any matches yet.
Well, I've scanned a total of 32 full
and partial prints from that fossil
but for every print that I scan,
dozens of possible matches...
come back. Then I have to check them
manually one by one to find a match,
so...
You know, I'm not David Caruso.
It takes time.
Well, you do your thing. I'm just gonna
take a quick peek at your list
if you don't mind.
Push hard on this one.
We need a rapid response.
Remember, any time
wasted's gone forever.
I'm not wasting time.
Are you suggesting
you don't have enough time?
You have exactly the same number
of hours in the day
that Albert Einstein had.
- Can you stop?
- Thomas Jefferson.
Louis Pasteur.
- Gandhi.
- Just get out of... here. Oh, my God!
Oh, my God. What do I do?
- What do I do? What do I do...
- Keep up the good work.
Montero was found at the archeology
museum with stab wounds.
Next to him, a display case
with a missing pendant
worth over $200,000.
The night of the murder Montero was
supposed to meet a prospective buyer.
- First, we thought the missing pendant...
- Hightower.
"We need to talk in private.
I'll meet you in my perch."
I don't have time now, Jane.
I'm in the middle of a briefing.
Yeah. I can see that.
Montero was running guns
to South America...
The Montero case has turned into
a high-priority murder investigation.
I can't just walk out.
I suggest you rethink what you can
and cannot do
from this moment forward
because I know who the evidence
is about to reveal as the killer.
Who?
You.
As a matter of fact,
they were best friends.
Montero's gun running operation
supplied Johnson with the weapon
that was used to kill our fellow officers.
We're working on the theory
that whoever took out Johnson
also took out Montero.
Excuse me, agents.
Urgent matter at my office.
So you're suggesting
both murders were part
of a vengeance play?
Yes, I am, sir.
Somebody wanted
both of these men dead.
"Johnson the cop killer..."
It suggests our killer has strong...
- Jane, this better be...
- Good. My sentiments precisely.
Where'd you get that?
I borrowed a key to the armory
from Lisbon's desk.
Are you a killer?
I don't know your game here
but I don't have time to be taken on
one of your emotional joyrides.
Not that I'm judging.
Seeking revenge on men
that are responsible for the death
of someone you love, it's a hobby
I like to dabble in myself.
You think it's true?
You think it's true that... that I killed
Johnson and Montero?
Well, let's just say I'm open-minded.
Any minute now, the lab
is going to identify your prints
at the Montero crime scene.
I have never been
to that museum.
Well, then you're either
being framed...
or you're a lunatic killer.
In either case
you should phone your family
'cause my guess is
the pot roast is gonna be served
a little late this evening.
If you don't point that shotgun
away from me
I swear I will use it to beat you
like a rented mule.
Spoken like a true lunatic killer.
You're not giving me much
to work with here.
I mean it.
So do I.
Did you kill those men?
I have to know.
Why, Jane?
If you think I'm guilty,
turn me over to LaRoche.
- I'll go.
- No.
If you killed Todd Johnson
then you're mine
and you're gonna lead me
straight to Red John.
Red John?
- What does this have to d...
- Todd Johnson was taken out
because he knew
Red John's secrets.
As if you didn't know that.
And if you didn't know it
the real insider
murdered Montero to frame you
which brings us the full circle.
Are you or are you not a killer?
You know what I am, Jane?
I'm a single mom...
with two innocent children
at home.
There's nothing in the world
I would do
to compromise their safety
or their future.
Please, Jane.
I've heard enough to convince me
that we're looking
for one killer here.
J.J., you take lead.
This is now
a double murder investigation.
Excuse me, Director Bertram, I'm sorry.
Sorry, everybody.
Um, you asked for developments
on the Montero case.
I think this qualifies.
This has to be a false positive.
No, I checked and double-checked
all the bifurcations.
- It's a clear match.
- What is it?
A mistake.
Hightower's prints
at the Montero crime scene?
Yeah. I'm not surprised.
Have another analyst verify
your findings.
- Yes, sir.
- Van Pelt...
start working on a search warrant
for Agent Hightower's home.
Is that really necessary?
She can always grant us consent.
She's in her office now.
I'll call over.
Contact the university police.
Find out if they have record
of a vehicle matching Agent Hightower's
on campus the night of the murder.
Ask them to check security footage.
Yes, sir.
I don't like the way
this is being handled.
Can we just take a moment
before we destroy a colleague's career?
Agent Hightower has been on top
of a short suspect list
in the Johnson murder for some time
even before Director Bertram notified me
that she was romantically linked
with one of his victims.
Now you're into her sex life?
Wow, when you boys decide
to destroy a woman's reputation
- you really go all out.
- Lisbon!
You're the one who just told me that the
Johnson and Montero murders were linked.
Now we have evidence.
If you're too close to this,
let me know
and I'll move you off this investigation.
- I'll be fine, sir.
- Hightower never went to her office.
I just spoke to her assistant.
That's my fault. I let her walk out.
I didn't think she would run.
Who said she's running?
For all we know, she's in the ladies room.
Maybe you should check.
We're going to conduct a search
of Agent Hightower's home and office now.
"Leave your name and number.
I'll get back to you as soon as I can."
It's Lisbon. Wherever you are,
do us both a favor
and call me as soon
as you get this, okay?
I can't believe we have
to go through the boss's stuff.
Suspect's a suspect.
Just feels so wrong, though.
Wait a second.
This drawer's too heavy.
Check it out.
False bottom.
The stolen pendant.
Hey, boss.
Oh, no.
Seems we found your mystery buyer.
Put an immediate B.O.L.O.
out on Madeleine Hightower.
She's considered to be armed
and dangerous.
- Where is she?
- Over here.
You saw the suspect?
Details, please. Where? When?
Uh, I was coming out
of the elevator after lunch.
Where was the suspect headed?
Uh, up the stairs,
which I-I thought was strange
'cause it leads to the roof, right?
Not just the roof.
It's where Jane works.
- Has anybody seen him?
- Not since this morning.
Cover the exits, all of them.
Use whoever you have to out here.
It's locked.
Jane?
- You in there?
- "Yeah, I'm coming out."
"You're gonna have to stand back
and if you're bearing firearms"
"please lower them."
"Please."
Stand back, or he dies.
Let us pass.
If you don't let us pass,
you can try to stop me
but just know that my finger
will reflexively pull this trigger
If I stumble or if I fall.
- Agent Hightower.
- Don't beat yourself up, Teresa.
There's nothing you could
have done to prevent this.
I got myself into it,
and I'm getting myself out
so clear a path.
Everyone.
Lower your weapons.
Let 'em pass.
- Walk.
- Walking.
Go ahead, Cho.
Make your move. Watch him die.
Nobody move.
Everybody just stay calm.
Put the phone down.
- You heard her. Put the phone down now!
- Put it down!
Okay...
Here's how it is.
We're exiting the building.
If anyone tries to stop us,
I pull the trigger.
If anyone in here calls anyone out there,
Do as she says.
Let's go. Move!
Hey, Jane.
That wolf's tooth you gave my kid?
Was a huge hit. Look at this.
He drew this. It's for you.
Kind of in a rush here, Jim.
Hey, stop!
Hey! Hey, hey! That's Patrick Jane!
Cho, get a chopper up and notify every
available CBI field unit.
I want visual contact
with the target
- but maintain a safe distance.
- "Roger that."
My car, you drive.
I'm a poor driver at speed.
I'm sorry.
- About what?
- Your boss. You admire her.
That's irrelevant.
We need to focus on Jane's safety.
"All units be advised"
"a single-vehicle traffic collision
on North Main."
"Vehicle is a dark-colored
late-model SUV."
Copy. We're en route.
30 seconds out.
- Wait for backup.
- You wait.
Hold all oncoming traffic.
We've got a suspect missing.
Set up a 10-block perimeter.
Notify the T.A.C. Team
and call an ambulance.
What happened?
She was unwrapping her hand...
the moment I was waiting for.
To crash the vehicle?
It seemed like a smart idea
at the time.
They think Jane may have a concussion.
They've taken him
to the hospital for a CT Scan.
I'm just thankful he's gonna be okay.
And where are we at
with our manhunt?
We have perimeter teams deployed
around the command post
for 16 city blocks.
U.S. Marshals have joined the hunt.
So's the FBI.
They put Hightower
on their most wanted list.
Such a tragic turn of events.
Look, there are worse things
that could happen here
than we have an open-and-shut case.
It's a blemish, to be sure
but at least we can close the book
on this ugly chapter at CBI.
"And when thy little heart doth wake"
"then the dreadful night shall break."
What's that?
Ah, it's just a... an old poem I like.
William Blake, I believe.
Why aren't you answering
your cell phone?
- Is it ringing?
- For two hours.
I'm sorry. I thought it was my brain.
Doctor said it's to be expected.
Of all people to use
to effect her escape
why would Hightower choose you?
Theoretically speaking,
I think it makes perfect sense.
I'm isolated in the rafters,
I don't carry a weapon
and I don't know any of that...
hand-to-hand combat jive.
I don't want theories. I want facts.
Why would she come to you?
You don't... honestly believe...
that I had anything to do
with Hightower's actions tonight, do you?
I honestly don't know what to believe
but whenever you're in the middle
of something
I have reason to doubt.
- And I like Hightower.
- When in doubt, don't.
Well...
Whatever happened tonight,
I'm glad you're safe.
Thank you.
Hey.
Thank you for coming
to my rescue.
I guess I should express my appreciation
to LaRoche.
Is he still out commanding the troops?
No. He went home for the night.
- Jane?
- LaRoche.
You have a fluffy white dog
and an entire...
house.
Are those hummel figurines?
Yeah.
You find that amusing?
Well, I just didn't picture you living
in an actual house.
Where did you think I lived?
In a burrow on a riverbank.
Somewhere like that.
What can I do for you, Jane?
You already did for me.
You let Hightower exit the building
instead of shooting me
in the brain stem
and for that, I'm thankful.
How'd you know I drink scotch?
You do?
Thank you.
It's my pleasure.
It's too bad she got away, though, huh?
Hightower.
Perimeter will remain in force
until we find her.
May take a day or two days
but we'll find her.
- She can't escape.
- Oh, she's escaped. I know it.
Just like you knew I was wrong
about Hightower's capacity for murder?
That's the counterpunch. Landed it.
Are we kids or what?
Yes.
We are kids.
Well, good night, Jane.
It is a good night.
Did it work? Right.
- Yes, it did.
- Did it work?
Okay.
I can't believe it worked.
"It will work."
- "This is crazy."
- "Not at all."
"Once they set the perimeter
you will be like a rabbit in a trap."
"They will search every vehicle leaving"
"except the car of the man
that is in charge so hurry, get in."
"Okay. All right. All right. How long...
how long do I have to be in here?"
- "Until you hear this."
- "Okay."
"Turn your cell phone off
so they can't trace you."
- "Here. Take mine."
- "Okay."
- "Whisper."
- "All right."
- Here's your cell phone.
- Did you make arrangements?
Yeah, I talked to my sister.
She's waiting for me just outside
town with my kids.
Perfect. You're gonna have
to completely vanish
because if Red John finds out
where you are
he will come after you.
She has a cabin in Saratoga.
We can wait there for a few months.
Perfect. He'll think he won this round.
Red John has a insider at the CBI
who framed me for murder.
I think it's safe to say he won this round.
Yes, but now I have the advantage.
With you gone, whoever it is
that works for Red John
will start to relax,
and thus lead me straight to him.
You risked a lot for me.
Well, not for you entirely.
I understand. Still...
thank you for getting me
out of that building
and back to my family.
And thank you for not shooting me
in the face.
No one can know about this.
This has to stay between you and me.
Jane, you should at least tell Lisbon
what's going on...
Nobody. He's too smart that way.
He'll sense a trap.
I'm better off alone.
Nobody is better off alone.